It's funny, isn't it?
Dead cars are quite beautiful
in their way
whereas dead people...
not so much.
I suppose if we were cars this place
would be a horrific Charnel house.
- It's too early for philosophy.
- Never too early.
- Hey, Cho!
- That's what I'm talking about...
Hey boss. She's over this way.
Hey, we've got an unidentified female
somewhere in her late teens, early 20s.
Oh, wow. A little notice
would've been nice.
Be grateful it's wintertime.
It could be a lot worse.
Looks like she was bludgeoned multiple times
around her left temple.
There's some serious blunt force trauma
to the back of her head as well.
Somebody wanted her good and dead.
How long has she been down?
From the decomposition of the body
she's probably been out
here at least a week.
- Is that the guy who found her?
- Yeah, a scavenger.
Came across the victim
when he was combing through the van.
It looks like somebody took something off
of her after she was already here.
A watch or a bracelet, I'm guessing.
Left the earrings though.
Found a set of tracks over there.
I think they're connected.
It's a salvage area.
There'd have to be lots of tracks.
Yeah, it's a long shot
but there weren't many tracks in the area,
and these look pretty fresh.
- Smells like transmission fluid.
- That's what I thought.
I'll have forensics run some tests.
Now if a vehicle with a leaking
transmission made the track
then the driver couldn't have gone
far without service.
- Hey, what's... what's his name?
- Franklin.
- Cool, it boy.
- May I?
I have a way with dogs.
Hey, Franklin. How are you?
Yeah, you're a good boy.
I thought you said
you had a way with dogs.
He wanted freedom.
- Franklin! Heel!
- Keep up, Lisbon!
Franklin!
What's that?
Franklin, come. Come on now.
Get out of there, Franklin.
It's a foot!
Another body. Are you done?
Hey, what do you say, Franklin?
Are we done yet?
Huh, we done?
The cadaver dogs didn't find
any more bodies, did they?
Thankfully, no.
The test confirmed there was a lot
of transmission fluid
in that track at the scene.
And the tire pattern only fits
a few specific van models.
I'm checking garages just to see
if any vehicles
fitting the description were turned
in with transmission problems
over the last week.
All right.
Cho, you mind helping him out?
- Is there a problem here?
- No.
- No, ma'am.
- Great. I see a name.
Did we I.D. the victims?
- Only on one.
- Got a hit on her prints.
It's for the second victim you found.
Her name was Valerie Bestin.
No next of kin.
She was arrested four years ago
after hitting a homeless man
while driving drunk.
The M.E. puts her time of death
within the last 24 hours.
Bestin was bludgeoned in the same
manner as the first victim.
What about an I.D.
on the other victim?
Her prints haven't come up yet.
The M.E. pegs her as Latina, early 20s.
Do a preliminary search
of the missing persons database.
- Maybe we'll get lucky.
- Yes, ma'am.
All right, we've got two victims...
one Caucasian
the other probably Latina.
At least a 10-year age
gap between them
and judging by their clothes,
Valerie had more money.
But both were bludgeoned
and dumped in the same place
one week after the other.
What's the connection?
Library, bowling alley, nail salon.
Could be anything.
Well, let's focus on
what we do know.
What about the homeless guy
Bestin hit?
He's been in a secure mental facility
since last year.
Speaking of mental facilities,
have you seen Jane?
I need to talk to him.
There you are!
Where's my couch?
Oh. Yes.
I bought you a new one.
- I like my old couch.
- No, you don't.
You've gotta try this one.
Let's discuss it later.
We have to talk.
- Have you ever been into knitting?
- What?
No, of course not.
You grew up surrounded by boys.
What are you talking about?
Hi there. You seem to have
very nimble fingers.
Are you now or have you
ever been a knitter?
No. Agent Lisbon.
Yes, Dr. Montague.
It's a pleasure to meet you.
- And you must be Patrick Jane.
- I must be.
You were saying we needed to talk.
Yes, Dr. Montague is consulting
on the case.
Yes, she's a decision science consultant.
She works with the FBI
and state agencies.
Her work helped bring
in the quarry killer.
I'm developing a predictive
computer model.
It identifies the patterns in crimes
and assesses whether or not they were
committed by the same perpetrator.
Wow. Cool.
The systems flagged your two murders
as the re-emergence of a killer
known as "the Caveman."
I remember him.
He bludgeoned his victims
with a wooden club.
That was ten years ago.
Indeed, but the similarities
between his victims
and the victims in this case
are statistically identical.
How so?
The Caveman always picks
two victims, one week apart.
The same physical attributes...
brunettes, 120 to 140 pounds.
In every other respect, the choice
seems entirely random...
no geographic or demographic pattern.
Victims are bludgeoned
on the side of the head
with a wooden object,
no evidence of sexual assault
bodies are left in waste sites
and scrap yards
and the victims are unknown
to each other.
This is classic Caveman.
Well, at least you're wrong with conviction.
These two women knew each other.
How do you know that?
Okay, so this one...
Yes, now if you look at the detail
in this rose
and then again at the detail in this scarf
they were both done by the same hand.
- Intriguing handicraft theory.
- Yeah.
But even if we were able to establish a link
between the victims
it doesn't exclude the Caveman
from being the killer.
It merely expands the modeling paradigm.
Merely expands the modeling paradigm.
Wasn't the Caveman known
for sending poetry, animal organs
even crude drawings to the police?
We haven't received anything like that.
- We will.
- Hey, boss.
Found out that Valerie Bestin
was a financial director
at an online company called Agile Turtle.
Dr. Montague, this is agent Wayne Rigsby.
Rigsby, Dr. Montague's consulting on the case
and you'll be her liaison.
It's a pleasure to meet you.
- Why don't you show her around?
- Sure, I can give you the 50-cent tour.
Start in the major crimes section.
Really? A decision science consultant?
Don't start. This goes way above us.
We're good to the feds,
the feds will be good to us.
When in doubt, don't act out.
You just made a rhyme.
When am I ever in doubt?
- Seriously, you start trouble, and I will...
- You'll burst my bubble?
She was such a good person.
She took all these underprivileged-like kids
hiking at half dome earlier this year.
Mr. Beechum, did Valerie
have any friends or co-workers
- that were young Latinas?
- Mm, no.
There's not really that many women
that work here.
You had a crush on her, didn't you?
- Why do you say that?
- She's an attractive young woman
single computer
programmer, birds, bees.
I could go on.
I'm more of an entrepreneur
than a programmer these days
but that isn't an untrue statement.
She was a lovely lady.
But when you made your move,
she shot you down.
No. Well...
Yeah, I wouldn't really call it a move.
But there were no hard feelings.
I mean, if I killed every woman
that shot me down
I would be a monster.
You know, well...I mean, I'm not...
You know what I mean.
- When was the last time you saw Valerie?
- Uh, yesterday at work.
Okay, I think we're done here.
- You do?
- Yes.
Oh, actually, no.
I have one more question.
Where's the nearest homeless shelter?
Valerie was deeply guilt-ridden
over hitting the homeless guy.
She started collecting soap,
shampoo, and crayons.
She was taking kids hiking.
- She probably volunteered her time...
- In a homeless shelter?
Sometimes you act like I don't know Jack.
More rhyming.
Now that's even rapping.
Sometimes you act
like I don't know Jack.
I'm-a drop a beat back there.
Yeah.
Yee-yee.
Valerie Bestin?
Of course. She volunteered here.
That's what I told the other people.
- What other people?
- Um, those people.
Hi.
How'd you know to come here?
Women are 17% more likely
than men to self-direct
into redemptive recourse
after committing crimes.
Given Valerie Bestin's lack of relapse
after D.U.I. with injury incident
it only made sense
that she would follow the pattern
so I called treatment facilities and shelters
in surrounding areas
until I found the right place.
So you... guessed.
Ah, it's more of a scientific
hypothesis, really.
- Just keep us in the loop.
- Noted.
Need to head back
and code these interviews.
If you'll excuse us.
You have to admit,
she really knows her stuff.
I'm admitting nothing.
She's huffing and puffing.
Wait. That rhymes.
Like I told Dr. Montague,
I didn't know Valerie very well.
But she would often bring
donations with her.
Desperately needed.
Ah, we're stretched pretty thin
around here
so our focus is on our guests.
Uh, but Paula had more contact
with her than I did.
Valerie was a saint.
She never talked down to nobody.
Always makin' sure we was eatin' better
drinkin' less.
Oh, when Marty died...
She was, like... cryin'.
She really cared.
- Marty?
- A former guest.
He passed away here a couple weeks ago.
A bad case of flu swept through here.
Lot of people got sick,
and poor Marty's system just...
Just couldn't handle it, you know?
Any other questions, Jane?
Uh, yes, um,
I do have one more question...
- Yeah.
- In fact.
Do either of you recall whether
Valerie was a-a knitter?
- Knitting.
- Thank you for your time.
All right. Thank you.
Just got back the forensics report.
Both victims were bludgeoned
with the same object.
Identical wood fibers
were found in both their wounds.
Sounds like the Caveman.
I don't think he has the patent
on killing with a 2x4.
You know, we should think
about a press response to this.
Being ahead of media speculation
makes us look less reactive.
Well, hang on.
We're not even sure it's the Caveman.
We don't need to speak
to the press just yet.
I disagree.
But I hear you...
and I understand your concerns.
Yes, you hear me, most certainly.
But I doubt very much you understand
my concerns.
If you're so sure
that it's not the Caveman
why are you reading up on his file?
I like to read.
I have insomnia.
I don't like warm milk.
I'm lactose-intolerant.
I could go on.
Did you know that habitual mockery
is a strong indicator of depression?
No. But thank you for enlightening me.
Um, that was inappropriate.
I apologize.
Oh, this is the last address.
One of these vans has to have been
at the salvage yard.
- How many left?
- Nine.
Oh, we already hit eight.
God, my feet hurt.
Your feet hurt?
Is there some way we can work this out?
What? I have to spell it out?
Okay, look, I lied.
I lied to the P.S.U.
to protect my dad
and you had to lie to cover me,
and I owe you big-time.
Look, I get that you're mad at me,
and I'm sorry.
But please, can we move past this?
- Okay.
- Okay?
What, like... like, we're okay, okay?
Police!
Hey, what the hell, man?
CBI. We need to ask you
a couple questions.
- You the owner of this van?
- Yeah.
You get your transmission
fixed this morning?
Yeah. Why?
- Ma'am, where'd you get that bracelet?
- At the none-of-your-damn-business store.
So did your friend Yasmeen
in the back of the van
- know where this bracelet came from?
- Oh, that wasn't a friend.
That was just a little dinner.
It's weird that your dinner's name
was Yasmeen
but this bracelet you gave
her has the initials "F.T." engraved on it.
Imagine that.
It's too bad you forgot the matching earrings
off the woman you killed.
I didn't kill anybody.
Then how'd you end up
with a dead woman's bracelet?
You know, decomposing bodies
can still leave a lot of evidence?
Only a matter of time before
they match up the D.N.A.
Left on this bracelet to her body.
Look... sometimes I haul junk
to that yard.
I was there looking around
for whatever.
There she was, already dead.
The bracelet wasn't doing her any good.
Too much of a wuss to be a killer.
Lacking in grandiosity, only one divorce
no traffic violations.
An undercurrent of rage would normally
express itself
at least in a driving record.
I'm not seeing a propensity
for violence here.
- So you agree with me?
- Not our killer.
Thank you.
The Caveman was never known
to steal jewelry off his victims
so that clears up that anomaly.
Life's just one giant mathematical
equation for you, isn't it?
I would like that. I confess.
- This isn't the Caveman.
- So you say.
I got $1 that says the same thing.
I have no objection to gambling.
You're on.
- Oh, someone's popular.
- Hardly.
What is it?
What the hell?
Looks like a kidney.
There's a poem on the other side
of that paper, I suspect?
You've seen this before?
"The ladies are dead.
I crushed their heads."
"And after the lash,
they go into the trash."
It's from the Caveman.
Poetry week. You could've done
better than that.
- I believe we had a wager.
- Ah. Yeah.
Thank you.
"We've received reliable notification"
"from an individual calling
himself the Caveman"
"who claims responsibility for the murder
of two local area women..."
- Hey.
- Ms. Montague in her element.
It's not often you see a profiler
basking in the spotlight.
Well, Montague says
that a killer like the Caveman
craves acknowledgment for his crimes.
Giving him some attention could keep him
from taking another victim early.
- You like Montague, don't you?
No.
- I mean, I... don't dislike her.
- What's to dislike?
Right. Still working on, uh...
where the Caveman
sent the package from
but we got an I.D.
on the other victim.
Excellent. Fernanda Talan.
Engraved initials on the back
of her stolen bracelet
"helped make a positive match."
"Her cousins reported her missing
about a week ago."
"She worked for them.
Dos Hermanos bottling plant."
Still wearing that brooch, I see
but where's the power suit?
Well, wearing a palette of neutral tones
is less threatening
when interviewing people.
- Hi.
- "Hey, boss."
I just got Valerie Bestin's phone records.
Lately she's been getting a lot of calls
from Donovan Treadlow
the homeless shelter director.
- He said he barely knew her.
- "Well, he lied.'
Take Cho. Get the story.
Fernanda was our cousin
from my mother's family.
She came to us to get away
from the violence in Oakland.
This wasn't supposed to happen to her.
Her brother was killed just last year,
and now this?
She was going to make it.
Calm down, Nilda.
When was the last time
you saw Fernanda?
About a week ago.
She took the bus after work
and just vanished.
We were worried immediately
when she didn't show up the next day
because she never missed work.
Where did she work?
- On the line.
- In there?
Have you seen Valerie Bestin
around your neighborhood?
No.
We only heard about her
through the news and you all.
I like the packaging.
What flavor is that?
Um... probably our orange cream sodas,
right, Esther?
Yes. We make natural sodas.
No corn syrup, no artificial flavors.
We employ locals, pay them right.
People used to shake their heads
when we first started
but now they're getting it.
Fernanda had made
a huge change here.
She wanted to be a nurse and...
It's just all so sad.
Is this a boy or girl?
I can't really see.
It's a boy.
A boy lizard.
What's his name?
- Chuy.
- Hey, Chuy.
Ms. Montague, you're awfully quiet.
I'm sure you have some questions.
Ms. Montague here...
she's, uh, super, super clever.
- She's a scientist.
- Thank you, Mr. Jane.
Oh, pleasure.
- Did Fernanda ever abuse alcohol?
- No.
What about illegal
or controlled substances?
What are you trying to say
that Fernanda got mixed up in drugs?
I'm looking into traits
and habits which might give
some insight
into why she was chosen by the Caveman.
Finding out why Fernanda's to blame
for getting murdered?
What kind of quack are you?
I'm sure that's not
what Dr. Montague meant.
Uh, it appears that you've got this covered
so I'm just going to, uh,
go inside and take a look around.
Ma'am, I did not mean to offend.
If you let me explain
my procedure to you...
Fernanda was a sweetheart,
hard worker.
She had gotten pretty sick
a couple of weeks back
- but there she was, on the job.
- Sick how?
Stomach bug, something.
- Dedicated.
- Absolutely.
Shy at first, but then
she really got into it
asking how we did things, you know
just learning the process.
Can I, um, try one of these sodas?
Absolutely.
Cheers.
Yeah, that's good.
What's, uh, what's happening
tomorrow night?
They're having a candlelight vigil
for Fernanda.
Is the Helios Street Line
difficult to get to?
No. Bus stop is right out front.
Hey!
Hey, uh, Lisbon's just finishing up
in there.
Won't be a moment.
- What'd you find out?
- Various things.
- All data is useful data.
- So nothing then?
And you?
Well, I found out how our two victims
were connected.
- How?
- Get on the bus. I'll show you.
Wait. But my car is...
Nah, just get on the bus.
Come on.
Mr. Treadlow, you had a late night
conversation
with Valerie Bestin the day
before she died.
You say you hardly knew her
and there you are calling her at midnight.
Why'd you lie?
How it looks is bad
but it was shelter business.
Your wife can confirm that.
- That's not necessary.
- Then tell us about those calls.
Valerie was always thinking she saw me
being too friendly with our female guests.
- What did she see?
- Me comforting them.
Never discount the power of healing touch.
So how often are you healing
the homeless women around here?
Don't make it sound so sordid.
If there were nothing wrong,
your wife would be standing here.
Look...
Valerie kept yammering about
how she was gonna tell my wife if I didn't.
So I was trying to persuade her
to let me handle it in my own way.
We've looked into you, Mr. Treadlow.
You and your wife started
running this shelter nine months ago?
Yes, when we moved to the area.
But this isn't the first time
you lived around here.
You worked construction here.
Ten years ago, right?
I did. What are you getting at?
Well, you left town
in the middle of a housing boom
just after a serial killer
named "the Caveman"
stopped murdering the local women.
And now you're back,
and here's the Caveman again.
Crazy, right?
Come on.
You need to come with us.
Please.
Now that, uh...
Brooch that you wear all the time...
Does it carry any special
meaning or significance?
- No.
- No?
I only own one piece of jewelry.
Saves time and mental energy.
That's very efficient.
- Lucky it looks very good on you.
- Thank you.
That's Agile Turtle.
So the office where Valerie Bestin worked
is on the same bus route as the factory
where Fernanda Talan worked.
The homeless
shelter's on the same line, too.
All right, that's... that's a very
suggestive link, but...
Lisbon? Yes, I ditched you.
Uh, I must confess.
But look at the bright side.
I left you with a car this time.
There's no need to be so grumpy.
It's okay.
I call bearing news.
Our victims met on the Helios line.
It's a bus route.
A bus.
Public transportation.
Yes.
And I would bet that the killer
met the victims on this same bus.
Well... it's always a pleasure.
Okay. Bye-bye.
- Pure surmise.
- Yes.
Pure.
Anything on the Jane bus angle?
I found out Valerie Bestin
barely used her car
even though she got her license back
a year ago.
She mainly took the bus,
just like Fernanda.
- Cho, I thought you were with Treadlow.
- We're letting him think a while.
I'm working with the D.A.'s office
to get all the personnel files
released by the bus company.
Van Pelt?
I'm running filters on all the riders
with bus passes to see if anything flags.
Nothing as of yet.
Okay, and when you're done with that,
find my old couch.
- There you go.
- Thanks.
I don't recall
there being a strong correlation
between the victims
and the use of public transportation.
The Caveman's adapting.
I'll need to update my model.
- Ms. Montague, just...
- Doctor. Dr. Montague.
- Dr. Ms. Montague.
- Just doctor.
- Doctor?
- Yes.
Montague.
Turn the super computer off.
Sit back, relax, and enjoy the ride...
And the company, if possible.
- Mr. Jane.
- Yes. Got it in one.
Yes. On a notion...
You have us sitting on a bus
because our victims
might have been on the bus
at the same time?
This is... messy.
Can I ask you a question
as professionals?
Two professionals... peers, if you will.
Why can't a notion, a thought, or an idea
just hang out there for a moment?
Just hang.
Because life is order and sequence.
Death is disorder, entropy.
Did you know that California
leads the nation in the number
of serial killers?
Top security, at least.
Excuse me.
Pardon me, ma'am.
Uh, I couldn't help but notice
the beautiful detail work in this scarf.
- Did you knit this yourself?
- Yes, I did.
That's very nice.
You know, you could sell these.
Do you... do you...
Have you thought of selling these?
Yeah.
You... you want to look?
If you don't mind.
They're very nice.
She's got some great stuff here.
Beautiful.
Can I just try this on my...
Lady friend?
Look at this. Look at that.
It's a very similar style...
- Stop.
- To the one that Fernanda was wearing
and it looks just terrific
with her ensemble, no?
Yes.
Excuse me, ma'am. Hello.
We're investigating the murder...
I'm so sorry. No understand.
- If I could just ask you...
- No understand.
But if you could
just wait a second, I...
Excellent people skills.
That's sarcasm.
We can work on that.
- Hey.
I was going through the personnel files
for the bus drivers
and something flagged.
A bus driver, his name
is Ralph Mercer.
He's only been with the bus company
for the last six months.
So?
According to his social security number,
he's been dead 15 years.
So I did a little more digging
and fingerprint records say
Mercer is actually Arthur Coffey.
Not a nice guy... long sheet,
including aggravated rape
and assault with a deadly weapon.
He drives the same route
our victims rode?
- Afternoon and evening shifts.
- Great. Where is he now?
Got his route schedule from his boss.
He's on the road now.
Hello, everybody.
I'm Patrick.
Uh, I'm sure you've all heard
about the two local women
found murdered. Yes?
Yes.
Fernanda Talan and Valerie Bestin...
They rode this bus every day.
Yes, they did, and we...
when I say "we"
I include my charming associate,
Dr. Montague.
We wanna know
what you know about them...
And any other shady people
that you may have noticed on the bus.
Any information may be important.
Any little piece of information may...
be important.
Anything at all?
Any detail?
Okay. Thank you.
Excellent people skills.
Ah, sarcasm. That's very good.
You're learning.
But, uh, I, in fact, got
an excellent response.
I'm told that the driver is a little shady.
- Really?
- Yes, really.
What the hell is goin' on? Huh?
How did you...
Why are you guys following me?
Uh, we'd like to ask you
some questions.
Are you cops, or...
No, we're consultants
with law enforcement.
Actually, no, she's with law enforcement.
I'm just an innocent bystander.
- She lured me into this whole mess.
- He's getting away.
- Do, uh, do something.
- That's good.
Like what? What am I gonna do?
Drop the weapon!
Facedown to the ground now!
That's nice timing.
Darn! With him in the back,
there won't be room for you two.
- Well, how are we gonna get back?
- Take the bus.
Come on, get up.
He was our driver.
Nice sheet, Arthur...
carjacking, extortion, rape.
Now that we've found 30 bindles
on you, we can add dealing as well.
I wanna straighten out, okay?
I got a disease... called addiction.
That's all it is... the dealing.
I'm just trying to, you know, maintain.
I'm a good person that made
some wrong choices.
Are you the firstborn in your family,
Mr. Coffey?
Yeah.
Ever heard of the Caveman?
Sure. From the... TV news.
You know these women?
Yeah.
They rode the bus.
They were killed by the Caveman.
I mean, it was just on TV.
In fact, yeah, it was you that was on TV
said it was the Caveman, right?
Yeah.
How many sexual partners
have you had?
Wow. You like to cut to the chase.
Um... like 100, 150.
Women? Men?
Hello. Women.
What is your point here?
We need to know
whether you killed these women
because they found out
about your side business
or because you're the Caveman.
Hey. No.
You think I'm the Caveman?
No, no. You got me all wrong here.
I deal a little blow, okay?
I don't do murders.
I think I'll take a lawyer now.
Well, he's the only suspect we have
with a direct link to both victims.
Yes, it's all very compelling,
but I'm not convinced.
And, yes, you should.
- Should what?
- Oh, you know what.
- No.
- Oh, yes, you do.
- No, I don't.
- Yes, you do.
That bus driver's an ass,
but he isn't the Caveman.
I'm thinking the same thing.
His shifts at work don't match up
with our timeline.
And without any hard evidence,
I had to cut Treadlow loose
so we have to start from scratch.
- Damn it to hell!
- Oh, language. Please.
Bertram is on Hightower's back.
She's on mine.
It's all, "catch the Caveman,
catch the Caveman."
I hate serial killers.
Caveman didn't kill Fernanda
and Valerie. Trust me.
Well, how can you be so sure?
Because I wrote the letter
from the Caveman.
What did you just say?
I wrote the letter from the Caveman.
- Yeah, I heard you the first time.
- Why'd you ask me to say it again?
- It was a rhetorical question!
- I just wanted to stir things up
just, you know, give Montague
a little prod.
- I get it. She irks you.
- No, she doesn't irk me. I like her.
In fact, she amuses me.
Yeah, and in the meantime,
everybody is freaking out
because they think
there's a serial killer on the loose.
Well, there is that, but...
that was her story.
- She made that up, not me.
- Undoing this is gonna be a nightmare.
The press is gonna have a field day.
I have to tell the families.
Isn't there a candlelight vigil
somewhere this evening?
Well, I think so.
It's all gonna work out just fine.
I have... no doubt in my mind.
- Dr. Montague.
- Agent Rigsby.
Interesting line of questioning
you had going in interrogation.
Oh, well, yes, as you know
sexual promiscuity and risky behavior
are reliable indicators in psychopathy.
Uh, yes, you can learn a lot about a person
from their sexual history.
I remember there was this one time
we had this guy in custody, and he had a...
It was a...
It's an inappropriate story,
sexual history-wise.
This has been, uh, nice.
- What has been nice?
- Talking with you.
Oh, well. You're welcome.
- Agent Rigsby.
- Yes?
- Your tea.
- Yes. I...
Will take that to go.
What, uh, agent Rigsby wanted to say...
Well, he... he wanted to ask you out
on a date tonight.
I was... going to go
to the candlelight vigil...
Oh, I got...
See, I picked that thing up. Um...
- What? What have you got now?
- This is for you.
Rigsby picked it out.
I didn't. I have no idea what's in that box.
You didn't...
- Yes, he did.
- No, I didn't.
Thanks for coming out.
Um, Fernanda's family was kind enough
to include us in this vigil
because we're all working
toward the same end.
We need to speak up.
We can't let a killer like the Caveman
hold our community hostage.
Don't let Fernanda and Valerie
die in vain.
Uh, if you have something to say,
please come forward.
Good evening.
Uh, excuse me.
My name is Patrick Jane.
Uh, I offer my condolences.
I'm a part of the team
that will bring this killer to justice.
I do have some unfortunate news.
We've just learned
that the letter we believed
to be from the Caveman is,
in fact, a very clever forgery.
- So what does that mean?
- Bottom line...
We're pretty sure that the Caveman
didn't kill your loved ones.
Someone is using the Caveman as a foil.
You all said it was him on TV.
The profiler lady said
you were making good progress on the case.
She made a mistake.
I'm sorry, but it happens.
So do you know anything?
Again, I'd like to apologize
profusely for our error.
Uh... it appears that this,
uh, forger is, uh...
one of unparalleled skill.
Oh! Oh, my God.
That's blood.
Oh. What is that?
- The profiler lady was wearing that brooch.
- Yes, she was.
I'm not a specialist,
but that looks like a kidney.
There's a note.
"Your profiler is dead."
"Stupid copycat
will join her at midnight."
Signed from the Caveman.
Oh, no.
Lisbon, where are you?
I need your help.
Listen, thanks for tonight.
I had fun.
So did I, Wayne.
Um, I enjoyed your funny
stories immensely.
Good. And I enjoyed your, uh...
Well, I learned a lot
about statistical analysis.
- I hope I didn't bore you.
- No, not at all.
Um, in fact, would you like
to go out again?
I would.
Uh... I would. Do...
You are an attractive
and stable character.
Thank you.
But I don't need to conduct an analysis
to see that you're still in love
with someone else.
The probability of us having
a successful relationship
- is no more than 20%.
- 20%?
Tops.
Where is everybody?
I thought we were working the night shift.
Oh, hi. Everybody's out
catching the killer.
Seriously?
No, I'm joking.
That was sarcasm.
Uh, they're out catching the killer.
Nilda, will you hurry up?
- What about Chuy?
- Forget the lizard already!
Essential items only.
Come on! Hurry!
What this?
It's the Caveman.
This is all a big mistake.
We never meant to copy you!
We just took the bodies
to the first place we thought of.
Nothing to do with you, I swear.
We had no idea!
Please don't do this!
I'm thinking this has to do
with your natural soda.
- Something not so natural in it?
- Well, that's no secret.
A lot of foods require additives
to keep them fresh.
Fernanda was giving her friend,
Valerie Bestin
crates of soda to distribute
to the homeless, right?
Yes.
Then a man at the shelter,
Martin Brent, known as Marty
died after drinking the soda, right?
- I don't know any Marty.
- Sure you do.
I'm only telling you this
so you know not to tell us stories.
Why would I lie about knowing
some homeless guy?
The assumption was that Marty died
because his system was too weak
to fight off the flu.
But when Fernanda got sick,
she started to do some digging.
You can't tie any of that to us.
A simple blood test will show
just what additives
were present in his system.
Everyone at the shelter
can confirm drinking the sodas.
Who gave them out
can be tested as well.
Esther said the soda
was losing too much flavor
so we started using glycol
as a stabilizer.
- We got a bad batch.
- How bad?
Esther said you had to drink a lot of it
in order for there to be any bad effects.
Most people just got an upset stomach.
It was only like 500 bottles.
You knew you were endangering
the lives of your consumers.
Esther said pulling the product
was too expensive
and kept saying it was no big deal.
Who drinks 12 bottles in one go anyway?
Right, and then the homeless man,
Marty, died.
Fernanda made the connection,
started asking questions.
Fernanda wouldn't let it go,
said we had to issue a massive recall.
She'd tell if we didn't.
And then you killed your own cousin.
Yeah, we did.
And then Valerie showed up a week
later, and you knew what you had to do.
I told Esther.
That lady didn't know anything.
But she kept saying someone like her
wouldn't stop coming around
and asking questions.
So she had to go.
Fernanda was my niece.
She was supposed to stick up for her own.
But she chose that bitch
on the bus over her family.
Thank you, man. I appreciate it. Really.
It's just soda.
- It's diet, right?
- Yep.
- Mr. Jane?
- Ms. Montague.
We have some important business
to conclude.
We do?
For you.
- I...
- Hang on.
Yeah, that's good.
- Okay?
- Thank you.
I always settle my debts.
You were right.
That wasn't a serial killer.
You remind me. I almost forgot.
Thank you. Forgotten it, too.
Useful brooch. Um, and I...
I was hoping that, you know,
you might forgive me
any misdirection I might have given you.
Oh, yes. No.
No, I... actually, it was bracing
to have one's operating principles
challenged
so... robustly.
Glad to be of service.
You know, I've never participated
in chicanery before.
I can't condone it as a system
but I must admit that it adds...
Zest to the task at hand.
In fact, w...
How did you figure it out,
that it was Esther and Nilda?
Just a good guess.
When we first met with them
they were masking shame, not sadness.
And who likes lizards?
Cold-blooded people.
Lizards.
- I think I shall stick with hard numbers.
- I have another guess for you.
The Caveman isn't coming back.
He is almost certainly dead.
Possibly. I have no personal
bias on the matter.
The numbers will eventually
reveal the truth either way.
They always do.
- You really believe that?
- Of course.
If you could stand
far enough back
to see the big picture,
everything is numbers.
Speaking of which...
You gave me a gift,
so I must give you one.
I ran Red John through
the modeling program.
You might find some
of the data sets useful.
- Wow. Lot of figures and graphs here.
- That's right.
Good luck.
Well, thank you.